# JOAQUIN LOPEZ

#### EMAIL | WEBSITE | GITHUB | LINKEDIN

SANTIAGO, CHILE

## ABOUT ME

Software developer and Computer Engineering student at the University of Chile. I have experience in Python and data processing libraries such as numpy, matplotlib, and pandas.

Additionally, I am proficient in several system languages and backend frameworks for web development, complemented by skills in frontend technologies. I also have knowledge of SQL and NoSQL databases, as well as massive data processing and graph processing for the web.

I am interested in developing software systems in embedded systems, topics related to semantic web, and networks.

## **EDUCATION**

University of Chile

2024

**B.S.** | Engineering Sciences with a major in Computing

Santiago, Chile

Professional Title | Civil Engineering in Computing (Currently pursuing)

## TECHNICAL SKILLS

High proficiency languages: C | Python | C# | Bash | Rust | SQL | HTML

Intermediate languages: Javascript | Java

Frameworks and libraries: Flask, Django (backend) | Bootstrap, vue (frontend) | Pandas, numpy,

matplotlib (Data Processing) | Hadoop, spark (Mass Data Processing)

Embedded Systems Frameworks: Arduino-IDE | esp-idf

Databases: PostgreSQL | MySQL | Sqlite | Neo4J

#### EXPERIENCE

#### Software Developer | Niclabs

Software development for DNS library in Rust

Sep 2024 - present

Santiago

- Implementation of specifications of various RFCs for a stub resolver
- Implementation of authentication functionalities with DNSSEC

## Software Development Intern II | CCHEN

Jan 2024 - Mar 2024

Development of a plasma camera control system

Santiago

- Implemented a camera control system for simultaneous photo capture
- Real-time camera configuration
- Ethernet network for data transfer

#### Software Development Intern I | SPEL |

Jan 2023 - Oct 2023

Software development for Cubesats

Santiago

The project consisted in the development of a software system for Cubesats written in C, which involved the following tasks:

- Port the software to a new platform (esp32 + FreeRTOS)
- Change the comunications library (libcsp)
- Implement a simple HAL for a gyroscope connected via  $I^2C$

Teaching assistant for various courses

- Introduction to Calculus
- Introduction to Algebra
- Discrete Mathematics for Computer Science
- Systems Software Programming
- Theory of Computation

### **PROJECTS**

 $\textbf{Thesis} \mid Semantic \ network \ extraction \ from \ dictionaries$ 

Jun 2024 - present

Generation and extraction of a semantic network from a dictionary of synonyms

- PDF scraping with Tesseract OCR
- Network generation from extracted data
- Implementation of a simple application to visualize the network using Neo4J and visjs
- Study of the network, its topology, and properties

Software Project: dnsrust | Niclabs

Mar 2024 - Aug 2024

Santiago

Software development for a DNS library in Rust

In this course with a team of 5 people, we worked a DNS library in Rust, which involved the following tasks:

- Implementation of shared key authentication TSIG
- Implementation of some DNSSEC security extensions
- testing and debugging of those implementations

## LANGUAGES

- English (C1 Advanced level)
- Spanish (Native)